American Association of Immunologists records
American Association of Immunologists records
1913-1996
bulk 1967-1992
1913 1996
Coll012
American Association of Immunologists
12 boxes (17 linear feet)
12 boxes
17 linear feet
Files documenting the American Association of Immunologists' (AAI) activities including correspondence, reports, minutes, ledgers, journals, newsletters, programs, directories, and audio visual materials. Of particular significance are membership dues ledgers and issues of the Journal of Immunology. Personal histories including articles, reports, correspondence and photographs are present for all the Presidents of the association.
University of Maryland, Baltimore County Albin O. Kuhn Library and Gallery UMBC 1000 Hilltop Circle Baltimore, MD 21250 410-455-2353 speccoll@umbc.edu
The collection of records of the American Association of Immunologists (AAI) primarily documents its activity between 1967 and 1992. While there are records back as far as 1941 they are very sporadic and consist mostly of correspondence. There are no documents concerning the Association’s founding and years up to the late 1940s, although there are articles included that relate the Associations history. The records are arranged in eight series: Council, Meetings, Committees, Financial, Historian, Publications, Affiliated Societies and Video and Audio Tapes.
The Council Series contains the records of Association Officers, Councillors, and the Executive Director. The Officer and Councillor files consist almost entirely of correspondence from the 1950s and 1960s though reports and meeting minutes are sometimes interspersed with the correspondence. The Executive Director files are those of Dr. Joe Saunders who was the first Executive Director of the Association and was appointed in 1986. His files include some materials of the Administrative Assistant dating from 1967 to 1971. The series Meetings contains files from the Annual/Business meetings, Council meetings, Executive Committee meetings and International Congress of Immunology meetings. The Annual/Business meeting subseries contains files for meetings from 1954 to 1992 with the exception of 1955. The Council meeting files begin in 1946 and are sporadic until 1965; from that point there is some material from each year until 1992. The index for Executive Committee reports and the accompanying reports were gleaned from meeting minutes and compiled in an easy to look up format. The system was devised by Executive Director Dr. Joe Saunders and is a good source to see what the various committees were involved in from 1973 to 1985. International Congress of Immunology files consist of correspondence pertaining to travel grants and arrangements with little information directly related to the meetings themselves.
Committee files are arranged in alpha order. The Education Committee files are the most numerous. There is more information on committees in the Meeting Series.
Financial records are extremely limited and in no way complete. There are two Association ledgers that cover the years from 1946 to 1970. The Membership Dues Ledger records membership records dating from 1921 provides a comprehensive member list. Also included are a small number of bank deposit and investment records, statements and a budget.
The Historian Series contains the files of the Associations first historian Merrill Chase. He was appointed in 1965 and began compiling histories and photographs of all AAI Presidents. Executive Director Dr. Joe Saunders added to Dr. Chase’s work. The files are in alpha order and include information and photographs of people other than AAI Presidents.
The Publication Series contains AAI publications such as newsletters from 1971 to 1991, meeting programs from from1960 to 1987. Although the Association published the Journal of Immunology since 1916, there are only volumes included from 1988 and 1989. The bulk of the material was not published by AAI but was included in the accession. It includes scientific articles, brochures, meeting programs and books. They are listed in alpha order.
Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology (FASEB), the International Congress of Immunology, the International Union of Immunological Societies and the New York Academy of Science Conference are included in the Affiliated Societies Series. The majority of the files are from AAI’s close relationship with FASEB and date from 1961 to 1990. There are FASEB yearly membership directories from 1965 to 1979. The files are in alpha order followed by date order.
Audio cassette tapes are available for some Annual and Council meeting from 1986 to 1991. The video cassettes contain interviews and lectures.
The American Association of Immunologists, Inc. (AAI) was formally chartered on June 19, 1913 in Minneapolis, Minnesota while the founders, Dr. Gerald Webb, Dr. A. Parker Hitchens and Dr. Martin Synnott were attending a meeting of The American Medical Association. Three principal objectives were set forth by the 52 enrolled charter members which were to unite the physicians of the United States and Canada who are engaged in the scientific study of immunity and bacterial therapy; to study problems of immunology and to promote by its concerted efforts a scientific research in this department; and to spread a correct knowledge of vaccine therapy and immunology among general practitioners. The Council established a liberal policy of admitting individuals with a doctorate and several years of teaching and/or research in immunology including publications. In 1972 the criterion for membership was modified and additional publishing requirements were imposed in order to create a more exclusionary Society.
In February of 1916 in Baltimore Maryland the Association began publication of its journal, The Journal of Immunology. The following year Association’s constitution and bylaws were adopted on April 6, 1917. There have been two major revisions in the Constitution since that time one in 1950 and the other in 1986. The alterations approved in 1950 expanded the classes of membership to include Honorary and Emeritus members and modified both election procedures and council membership requirements. The 1986 Constitutional revisions expanded the Council, called for the election of the nominating committee, gave formal recognition to Corporate Members, changed the entitlements of Emeritus and Honorary Members, replaced the Editorial Board with a Publications Committee and changed the management of the Journal and the Editor in Chief.
AAI’s Council has the duty of general supervision of the affairs of AAI between annual business meetings. The voting members of the Council include the President, Vice-President, Secretary-Treasurer, and four Councillors. Chairs of the committees may also be asked to attend Council meetings as non-voting members. They meet prior to the annual business meeting and at other times deemed necessary by the President and three voting members of the Council.
In the early years and until 1939 AAI scheduled its annual business meetings to coincide with the meetings of the American Association of Pathologists and Bacteriologists. However at the 1938 meeting of the Council and membership at large, a decision was reached to convene joint sessions with the Federation of the American Societies of Experimental Biologists. In 1942 AAI was formally invited to join the Federation as a Corporate Member Society. From that time and at least until 1991 the annual business meetings have been held in conjunction with FASEB.
For the first fifty years, the Association had no fixed location for executive activity. During that time the AAI headquarters was either in the residence or the professional offices of the Secretary/Treasurer. In 1965 a permanent headquarters was established for the administration and management of Association affairs at Beaumont House in FASEB headquarters. In 1980 the Council initiated moving the editorial office of The Journal of Immunology to the AAI Central Office at FASEB. At this time AAI began a search for an Executive Officer who would also serve as the Managing Editor for the Journal. Three years later President Barry Bloom appointed Dr. Joseph Saunders the first professional executive officer of the Association.
In 1968, the Council approved the appointment of a historian to assume responsibility of collecting letters and photographs of past AAI Presidents and people of historic significance to the Association. Past President Merrill Chase was selected as the first historian and began collecting as much primary source data as possible about the previous AAI Presidents. Dr. Joseph Saunders assumed the role of archivist as one of his duties as Executive Director in 1983 and collected more data.
Currently AAI is the largest professional association of immunologists in the world. It is still affiliated with FASEB and continues to have its headquarters located with the FASEB.
Organized into eight series: Series I. Council, 1941-1992. Series II. Meetings, 1954-1993. Series III. Committees, 1966-1992. Series IV. Financial, 1921-1991. Series V. Historian, 1913-1988. Series VI. Publications, 1933-1995. Series VII. Affiliated Societies, 1967-1991. Series VIII. Video and Audio Materials, 1970-1991.
Series I. Council
Councillors
Executive Director
President
Secretary/Treasurer
Series II. Meetings
Annual/Business
Council
Executive Committee
International Congress of Immunology
Series III. Committees
Series IV. Financial
Series V. Historian
Historian Records
Personal Histories
Photographs
Series VI. Publications
Series VII. Affiliated Societies
Series VIII. Video and Audio Materials
No restrictions.
Finding aid available.
MSS 1996-03; The records in this collection were donated in a single gift on March 29, 1996. The donation was approved by Dr. Michelle Hogan and the materials transferred from the Society’s offices in Bethesda, MD.
American Association of Immunologists Archives; Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology Archives; Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology; Immunology Societies, etc.; Saunders Joe
American Association of Immunologists. Accessed November 13, 2015.
- Series I. Council, 1941-1992; 1986-1992 bulk; 3 boxes (4 linear feet)
  The Council Series consists of four sub-series which made up the organization’s Council. They are the Councilors, Executive Director, President and Secretary/Treasurer. The general correspondence of each sub-series is in date order followed by subject correspondence in alpha order.
  - Subseries I.A. Councilors, 1941-1986; .25 linear feet
    All the files contain correspondence of a miscellaneous nature.
    - Correspondence 1941, 1943, 1954 -1956 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (Chase) 1954/4 -1955/2 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence (Metzger) 1986/5 -12 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Subseries I.B. Executive Director, 1967–1992; 1986 –1992 bulk; 1.75 linear feet
    The materials are primarily the files of Executive Director Dr. Joseph Saunders. He was the first professional Executive Director and was appointed in 1986. Many files contain a combination of correspondence and reports. They have been kept in the same arrangement as Saunders had them as much as possible. The files are listed in subject alpha order and then in date order. General Correspondence files are in date order and files preceding the subject correspondence files.
    - Actions Completed 1992/4–6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Administrative Assistant (Reines) 1967/1- 1971/12 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Agreements 1990/9 –1991/3 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Awards 1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Castaneda 1986 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Committee Reports 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence 1986/3 – 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence 1988/1 – 3 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence 1988//4 –12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence 1989/4 – 1991/3 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence 1991/4 – 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence 1991/10 –1992/9 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/AAI Symposium 1986/8 –1988/5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/AAI Annual Meeting 1988 1987/8 – 1988/6 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/AAI Annual Meeting 1990 1988/11 – 1990/5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/AAI Annual Meeting 1991 !989/6 –1991/4 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/ Bang Scholarship 1986/11 – 1987/6 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/ Behring-Heidelberger Lecture 1988/4 –1990/3 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence/ Behring-Heidelberger Lecture 1990/4 – 11 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence/ Behring-Heidelberger Lecture ( McDevitt) 1991/4 – 1992/4 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence/ Committee Members 1991/9 – 1992/8 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Correspondence/Committees 1987/6 – 1988/4 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence/Congressional Hearings 1991/1-3 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence/Congressional Hearings 1991/4 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence/Congressional Hearings 1991/5 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence/Congressional Hearings 1992/1 –2 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence/Cooper 1988/5 –1989/1 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence/Cooper 1989/4 – 1990/4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence/Council Meeting 1987 1987/3 – 9 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence/Council Meeting 1988 1988/5 –10 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence/Council Meeting 1989 1989/3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence/Council Meeting 1990 1989/11 – 1990/5 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence/Finance Committee 1989/12 – 1990/5 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence/Fitch 1991/11 – 1992/6 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence/Funding Requests A 1991 – 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence/Funding Requests B 1991 – 1992 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence/Heidelberger 1988/3 – 1989/11 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence/Heidelberger Death 1991/2 – 1991/9 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence/Honorary Members 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence/International Congress of Immunology Budapest 1991/3 – 11 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence/International Union of Immunological Societies 1992/2 – 6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence/Journal of Immunology 1988 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence/Meetings 1990 – 1993 1990/1 –1991/3 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence/Metzger 1991/7 – 1992/7 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence/Nisonoff 1990/8 – 1991/12 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence/Paul 1986/7 – 1987/12 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence/Program Committee 1989/11 – 1990/4 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence/Publications 1985/10 – 1986/4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence/Resolutions 1990/10 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence/Sandoz Prize 1989/2 – 1990/11 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence/Shreffler 1987/4 – 1988/6 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence/Thorbecke 1988/2 – 1990/9 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - History Articles (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Meeting Location Materals (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Membership 1988 – 1990 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Membership 1989 – 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Statistics (Scientific Program) A 1987 – 1991 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Statistics (Scientific Program) B 1987 - 1992 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Subseries I.C. President, 1947–1992; .5 linear feet
    The President sub-series contains all correspondence files. Occasionally reports are included within the files or are referenced in the correspondence. The correspondence is listed in date order with the President’s name. The correspondence was not all necessarily created while the person was in office.
    - Correspondence (Enders) 1945/11 – 1953/11 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence (Heidelberger) 1947/3 – 1948/11 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence (Enders) 1955/3 – 1968/9 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence (Chase) 1956 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence (Chase) 1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence (Chase)/Constitutional Revison 1955/10 –1958/9 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence (Smadel) 1957/2 –1959/2 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence (Dingle) 1957/5 – 1959/2 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence (Coons) 1960/2 – 12 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence (Lancefield)/Dr. Lee 1961 –1962 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall) 1967/5 – 1968/7 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/American Academy of Science Representives 1967/6 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Committee to Study National or International Congress on Immunology 1967/6 – 1968/3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Federation Board 1967/4 – 5 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Membership Committee 1967/4 – 5 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/National Medal of Science 1967/1 – 5 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Nominating Committee 1967/6 – 1968/3 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/ Public Affairs Committee 1967/6 1968/1 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Public Information Committee 1967/6 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence (Horsfall)/Translation Supplement Federation of American Societies for Experimental Biology 1967/4 – 9 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence (Enders)1968/4 – 1969/5 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Correspondence (Campbell) 1972/8 – 1973/7 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence (Campbell)/Committees 1972/6 – 1973/5 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    - Correspondence (Metzger)/Fitch 1992/4 – 5 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Subseries I.D. Secretary/Treasurer, 1953-1980; .5 linear feet
    The sub-series contains primarily correspondence, but there are reports, financial statements and information on meetings in some files. They are listed in date order.
    - Correspondence (Sugg) 1953 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    - Correspondence (Cheever) 1954/9 – 1961/2 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Correspondence (Howe) 1960/4 – 1961/5 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Correspondence (Howe)/Dr. Coca’s death 1959/12 – 1961/2 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Correspondence (Waksman) 1961/4 – 1963/2 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Correspondence (Waksman) 1963/3 – 1964/4 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Correspondence (Dray) 1963 –1969 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Correspondence (Dray)/International Congress of Immunology 1966/6 – 1967/1 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - Correspondence (Metzger) 1970/10 – 1980/2 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- Series II. Meetings, 1954-1993; 4.5 linear feet
  The Series II folders contain a variety of information on the annual and council meetings. Varying records are in the files including minutes, reports and correspondence. It is arranged in date order by year and then in alpha order if additional files were found for that year. The most information is available from 1986 to 1993.
  - Subseries II.A. Annual/Business Meetings, 1954-1993; .75 linear feet
    The annual business meeting was held in conjunction with the FASEB meeting. The files are arranged in date order and contain a variety of different items varying from year to year. Correspondence, reports, minutes and personal observances are available for many years. There is not a complete run of years.
    - 1954 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - 1956 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - 1958 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    - 1959 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - 1960 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - 1961 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - 1962 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - 1963 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - 1963/Correspondence 1962/6 – 1963/2 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - 1964 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - 1964/Correspondence 1963/5 – 1964/12 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - 1964/Display Materials (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - 1965 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - 1966 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1969 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1970 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1987 – 1993/Miscellaneous (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1988 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1988/ Correspondence (Celebratory Symposium) 1987/3 – 1988/2 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1990 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1990/Correspondence 1990/2 – 6 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1990/Funding Requests (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - 1990/Speakers and Abstracts (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - 1991/Abstract Control (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - 1992 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - 1993/Arrangements (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - 1993/Correspondence 1990/7 – 1992/5 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - 1963 – 1964/Programs (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - 1966 – 1977/Programs (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Subseries II.B. Council, 1946-1993; 2.33 linear feet
    The files are arranged in date order followed by committee report index and the corresponding files. Correspondence, reports and minutes are variously included for different years. Two council meetings a year were held beginning in 1986. The Council meeting files from 1986 to1993 were those compiled by the Executive Director.
    - 1946, 1948, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - 1954 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - 1957 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - 1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - 1965 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - 1969, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - 1972 (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - 1974 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - 1976 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - 1979 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1981 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1982 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1984 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1985 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1986/April (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1986/November (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1987/March (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1987/October (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - 1988/April (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - 1988/May (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - 1988/October (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - 1989/March (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - 1989/November (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - 1990/June (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - 1990/October (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - 1991/April (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - 1991/November (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - 1992/April (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - 1992/November (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - 1993/May (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Committee Report Index 1965-1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Committee Report Overview I – VI 1965 – 1985 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Committee Report Overview VII – XVIII 1965 – 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Committee Report Overview XIX – XXXVII 1965 - 1985 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Teleconferences 1990, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Subseries II.C. Executive Committee, 19731986; .3 linear feet
    The sub-series is an arrangement of committee reports taken from the council meetings from 1973 – 1986. The index listed what reports are included with a corresponding numeral.
    - Committee Overview Report Index 1973 – 1986 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Committee Overview Report I – VIII (II missing) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Committee Overview Report IX (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Committee Overview Report X (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Committee Overview Report XI – XVI (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Committee Overview Report XVII – XXIV (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Committee Overview Report XV – XXXIII (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Subseries II.D. International Congress of Immunology, 1990, 1992; .1 linear feet
    This sub-series contains grant application, travel grant awards and correspondence regarding the Congresses.
- Series III. Committees, 1966-1992; .75 linear feet
  The Committee files contain mostly correspondence and reports. The files are arranged in alpha order followed by date order. The Education Committee files also have curriculum description of courses.
  - Clinical Immunology 1990 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence (Saunders)/ 1989 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Education 1986 – 1987 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Education/Correspondence 1990 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Education/High School Teacher Internship Program 1990 (Box 6, Folder 22)